<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Autoscalinggroup on Svādhyāya</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/autoscalinggroup/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Autoscalinggroup on Svādhyāya</description>
    <image>
      <title>Svādhyāya</title>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 00:06:26 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/autoscalinggroup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Deploy Your Application With AWS AutoScalingGroup</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/deploy-your-application-with-aws-autoscalinggroup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 00:06:26 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/deploy-your-application-with-aws-autoscalinggroup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my previous post I wrote about process of pre deployment. A common question was about the deployment process itself. And the idea of this blog was born. The following is a non
exhaustive common list of ways to deploy to cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a single VM instance. For eg. Droplet(Digital Ocean), EC2(AWS), Compute Engine(GCP), etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In one or more VM instances with autoscaling. Not all cloud providers currently support this. AWS, GCP and Azure currently does it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managed Kubernetes Service (Supported by most common coud service providers) - Kubernetes is a way to deploy docker containers as seperate services. This is an extremely popular
option for microservices architecture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elastic Container Service - A proprietary service from AWS which is similar to Kubernetes but much less complicated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our use case we will be using option 2 - an Auto Scaling Group in AWS to show how the deployment should be done. AutoScaling Groups will cover most common scenarios
as well as be cost efficient. We will be using AWS Console to setup the AutoScalingGroup and the focus will be only to how to get the setup up and working. Aspects like security, optimal scalability is beyond the scope of this article.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
